Penelope Pennington Collection, 1798-1827: Finding Aid
Princeton University Library. Special Collections.
Penelope Pennington Collection
1798-1827
C0002
Princeton University Library. Special Collections. Manuscripts Division One Washington Road Princeton, New Jersey 08544 USA
0.2 linear feet 1 half-size archival box
Pennington, Penelope, 1752?-1827.
Consists of selected letters and manuscripts of Penelope Pennington, who was part of the social and literary women's group that was centered around the English diarist and patron of the arts Hester Lynch Thrale Piozzii (1741-1821).
Penelope Pennington was a friend and correspondent of Hester Lynch Thrale Piozzi, Mrs. Siddons, and Anna Seward.
The collection consists of thirty-one letters by Mrs. Pennington, mostly to her younger friend Maria Brown, whose relationship to Mrs. Pennington somewhat paralleled that of Mrs. Pennington to Mrs. Piozzi (Hester Lynch Thrale Piozzi); the autograph manuscript of Mrs. Pennington's poem "The Copper Farthing"; and over 200 pages of material, mostly in Mrs. Pennington's hand, largely copies of poems by her friends and literary quotations which apparently served the purpose of a commonplace book. The gossipy letters comment on politics, criticize books just read, and complain about bad health--not unlike letters of Mrs. Piozzi. Specific topics include the deaths of Maria Siddons and Mrs. Piozzi, Byron's poetry, and the peace of 1814.
The collection is open for research.
Three gifts: two from Robert F. Metzdorf in 1958 and 1961 and one from Mrs. Knight Woolley in 1958. Additional purchase in 1969.
No appraisal information is available.
Brown, Maria, 18th cent.; Piozzi, Hester Lynch, 1741-1821 -- Friends and associates.; Commonplace books -- England -- 19th century.; British literature; Women's studies
- Letters to Maria Brown and Others, 1798-1814, 1 folder (Folder 1)
  Contains 5 AMs letters.
- Letters to Maria Brown and Others, 1817-1821, 1 folder (Folder 2)
  Contains 14 AMs letters.
- Letters to Maria Brown and Others, 1822-1827, 1 folder (Folder 3)
  Contains 12 AMs letters.
- AMs, "The Copper Farthing," a poem, 7 p., undated; 1 folder (Folder 4)
- AMs from Commonplace Books, 1744-1789, 1 folder (Folder 5)
- AMs from Commonplace Books, Undated (1), 1 folder (Folder 6)
- AMs from Commonplace Books, Undated (2), 1 folder (Folder 7)
- AMs from Commonplace Books, Undated (3), 1 folder (Folder 8)
- AMs from Commonplace Books, Undated (4), 1 folder (Folder 9)
- Thorpe, James: Writings about Penelope Pennington, 1960; 1 folder (Folder 10)
  Essay about Pennington is from The Princeton University Library Chronicle.
- 32101040679134 (Box 1)